[Music]
Stanford
University we haven't discussed um units
at
all and let's let's discuss units a
little
bit in hron
physics we've dis we've um discussed the
idea
that a hron is a string and that it can
be excited that it can be excited by
setting it into rotation or setting it
into
vibration
uh by exciting the harmonic oscillators
that make up the stringy character of
the
uh of
the proton or whatever it happens to be
there's a certain energy scale or a
certain amount of energy that that each
excitation will give
you in particular the energy jump from
the ground state to the first excited
state how much is it what does it depend
on well in a string theory there's
really only one
parameter we talked about a little bit
we discussed the idea that if you
stretch a string let me just go back a
little
ways um if you stretch a
string from one point to
another then it behaves pretty much like
a spring it does behave like a spring it
has an energy if this is a
nonrelativistic string just an ordinary
non-relativistic string a rubber
band or an idealized rubber band its
energy its potential
energy let's call it
e what is hooks law
give for the
energy some K which is some spring
constant times the separ times the uh
square of the distance between the end
points missing something factor of
two
okay yeah that's the potential energy
that's in a string and uh and we've
identified energy this non-relativistic
energy we've identified it not with the
mass of the string but with a square of
the mass of the string why because we're
thinking about this in a frame of
reference where the string is moving
very very fast and when non-relativistic
physics actually works for the motion of
the string perpendicular to the
direction of motion so let's keep that
in mind we're looking at a string that's
going down the z-axis like this it it's
been stretched to a distance X or let's
call it
l let's called distance L this becomes l
s and we've
identified the energy with the square of
the mass
l^2 there is some spring constant
okay uh that spring constant I'll just
call K it says that the mass of the
string which in the rest frame in the
frame of rest at which the string is at
rest that mass is the usual energy
that's going to be the square root of
that spring constant time L perhaps
divided by the square root of two I'm
not interested in square roots of two
now so the mass of a stretch string is
proportional to its length times
some parameter which I've called the
square root of
K the square root of K has another name
it's called the
tension it's the tension in the string
the energy per unit
length like a mass now we have a string
at rest we're not looking at it in this
frame in which it's moving fast its
energy is its mass we stretch it
we stretch it out and the energy of it
grows proportional to the
length it's like surface tension except
now it's linear tension instead of
surface tension energy proportional to
length the coefficient is called tension
it's the tension in the string and so
there's a tension which is just the
square root which is just the square
root of K we don't even need to call it
square root of K we can just call it
tension
right now how much energy do we
get for each oscillation for each
oscillation oh yeah what is what are the
units of a square root of
K let's work in our favorite units in
which the speed of light and plunks
constant are equal to one in those units
energy has units of one over
length so if energy has units of one
over
length what's the units of Kappa here a
square root of Kappa the string
tension yeah it's energy squared or one
over length squared energy squared if
you like so this object over here let's
call it t t for
tension that tension in the string is
the thing which sets the fundamental
scale
uh
and it sets the scale for everything it
get it sets the scale it has units of
energy
squared and I'll tell you what it does
it tells you that each excited state
each time you excite the string by one
unit it adds to its mass squared
essentially that tension it adds to the
so the thing which has units the which
determines the units of the theory are
this string
tension the bigger the string tension
the bigger the jump in Mass when you
excite
something uh the same thing is true of
an ordinary spring incidentally if you
have an ordinary
spring if you have an ordinary
spring Let's uh let's take the mass of
the spring to be one the spring constant
call it K the
frequency is is just well it's a square
root of k k/
m the frequency is proportional to this
tension and of course the energy that
you bump up the Str the spring by every
time you excite it is also proportional
to Omega so the energy jump the energy
jump between the ground state the first
excited state next excited state and so
forth is controlled the unit is
controlled by this string
tension okay you could ask what is the
string and string tension is force per
unit or or sorry is energy per unit
length you know another name for energy
per unit
length energy per unit
length
force force force time length is energy
force time work force time distance
is
work right so all this tension
is is if you pull this apart that's how
much force is pulling you
back that's how much force is pulling
you back it's the force
within the string another way to say it
is if you took one of these strings at
the surface of the Earth and you
anchored it at some place and suspended
away from it
it would be the weight that the spring
that the string could
support a heavier weight would just
shrink or would fall
down uh smaller weight would be pulled
up okay that's the character of these
strings if you had one in the
laboratory the force the weight that it
can
support is independent of its length
incidentally you see that from this
formula you see that from the formula
that mass or energy same thing energy is
equal to Spring con or tension times
length force is energy per unit
length energy per unit length is
force and so the force that this string
can support is independent of its length
that's the character of these
strings
okay so then you could ask how
much weight at the surface of the
Earth how much weight could a um a
hadron a Meson if you could somehow
anchor one of the quirks in a
Meson uh to some support over here the
ceiling how much weight could a Meson
support and the answer is about a truck
about a uh I can't remember if it's an
18 wheel truck or a 16 wheel truck or
maybe it's on maybe it's just a half ton
panel truck I don't remember but it's
that order of
magnitude
um that's what a Meson could
support so they're pretty strong they're
microscopic little things but they're
pretty darn strong and the stronger they
are the higher the frequency of the
oscillations and so the larger the gap
between the lowest energy State and the
highest energy State how do I actually
know this did anybody ever support a
truck with a with a with a hyron of
course not what we actually know is the
amount of energy that it takes to excite
string and from that we deduce what the
tension is and from the tension I can
then tell you what you can
support these are are not the
strings that string theorists imagine
are associated with really fundamental
particles like gravitons photons and so
forth those
strings are much much
stronger very much stronger the tension
in them is vastly
larger if again you took the
Earth
and you supported a weight namely the
weight of the whole
galaxy
galaxy now of course this is nonsense
it's not the Galaxy that's going to move
it's the Earth that's going to move but
if you could concentrate if you could
concentrate a mass of the Galaxy in some
small
volume and make the Earth heavy enough
now you say if I make the Earth heavier
I increase its gravitational field fi
well not necessarily so we can make the
Earth much bigger but keep its
gravitational field the same if you
could somehow keep the
gravitational acceleration the
acceleration due to gravity the same
then the weight that you could support
would be about the weight of the
Galaxy so the strings that we're talking
about in fundamental String Theory are
vastly higher intention much higher
intention the meaning of that is that
the in
in an excitation to excite the string is
much much larger these are much stiffer
strings they have much much larger
spring constants and therefore much
larger frequencies of
oscillation if larger frequencies of
oscillation then larger energies in
exciting them how much
energy well the thinking goes that it's
probably somewhere up near the plunk
energy if we're talking about
gravitons uh it's the gravitational
scale does everybody know what the plunk
energy is I know I know you've heard of
it do you know actually what it is first
of all in first of all in numerically
and second of all what it actually uh
where comes
from
yeah Time c^
s right that's a that's a fairly big
energy it's enough to
um
that's a Car
Bomb boom how much was it I didn't hear
h i how much we didn't hear it 10us 5 G
10us 5 gr and and then you take that and
square and multiply it by the square of
speed of light right but when I asked
you if you know what the plunk energy is
or the plunk length or the plunk
whatever it is I was asking a more
theoretical question I was asking do you
know what it is in terms of the of the
other constants of nature maybe we
should go through that I mean this is
this is worth
doing also how long are these strings
you ah okay no that's the other question
that's the other question the stiffer
they are the smaller they
are now of course you can stretch them
out to any length there's no limit to
what you can stretch them to but if you
ask how much in their ground state
remember things in their ground state
oscillate how much do they oscillate in
their ground state then what's the
what's the mean
fluctuation in the size of these strings
the vibrations of them then the larger
the spring constant the smaller they
are they're much stiffer much harder to
pull
apart pulling this thing apart by 1
cm may cause you will cause a lot
of the smaller the bigger the spring
constant is
all right so how big do people think
they are oh somewhere of order the plunk
length the plunk Mass the plunk
length how fast is one vibration the
plunk
time okay so let's talk about these
plunk units there there's some reason to
believe it's a little bit smaller than
that maybe a factor of 10 maybe a factor
of 100 smaller but uh but that's a
that's a fine
point so let's talk about what the PL
length is I didn't prepare this so we're
going to have to work it out in real
time what is the plunk uh plunk length
what are plunk units first of
all what are any
units um in physics we need to have
three units Mass length and
time and our usual choice of units is
the usual units that we use in the
laboratory are not determined by any
fundamental physics the
meter is a convenient unit for um for
measuring rope okay that's where it came
from measuring rope you you measure rope
like that or cloth or whatever it is um
so no doubt it originated uh from the
length of a human
arm probably a foot of course is also a
similar kind of unit and it I assume
came from somebody's foot the king's
foot uh so what's the real physics
then or what's the real science of what
a meter is the real science is how many
atoms does it take to make a length of
an arm a useful arm has nothing whatever
to do with any fundamental physics has
to do with Biology how long it takes to
make an arm not a very deep unit that's
mass mass same thing a kilogram is a
kind of weight that you can manipulate
in the laboratory and a second a second
is about the time that you could measure
with a pendulum that's it that's where
they came from and they have no deeper
meaning than
that we would like for really
fundamental reasons in physics to choose
units which have some very fundamental
meaning now for example and if we
do then many of our equations will be
much simpler
for
example if uh the size of a proton comes
into various equations in nuclear
physics and the size of the proton is 10
Theus 13 cm if we work in centimeters or
10- 15th meters there going to be 10- 15
all it's not just 10us 15th it's 1.73
498 and physics is going to be very
messy on the other hand there's nothing
to prevent us
from saying let's use the unit in which
the radius of the proton is exactly
one then Nuclear Physics will turn out
to look a little bit simpler and it will
Nuclear Physics will turn out to be a
little bit simpler but Atomic physics
won't look a hell of a lot
simpler
uh the physics of subnuclear
particles sub hydronic particles will
not look a lot simil
there's nothing Universal about the
proton the proton is just some particle
that's all why use the proton instead of
some other particle no good
reason so there's nothing really
Universal about the proton and uh the
rules of physics will not in any way be
especially simple if we use the
proton
um Time same thing so we would like
three units which have some deep
fundamental significance ific an it's
equivalent to saying we would like to
choose three constants of Nature and set
them equal to one it's completely
equivalent to choosing three units to
choose three constants of
Nature and set them equal to one
constants of nature now mean dimensional
constants right the size of the proton
is one but that's not a good one you
want to use things which are really
which really are very Universal three
constants there are three constants in
nature which are truly Universal and
I'll tell you what they are the first
constant is the speed of
light why do I say it's Universal
because there's a rule and the rule is
nothing can move faster than the speed
of light nothing everything move is
every velocity of every material object
is bounded by the speed of light the use
of the word every there tells you
there's something fundamental about it
that there's something uh whether it's
protons or elect Rons or photons or
anything else they all are bounded by
the speed of light so there's something
Universal about the speed of light yeah
well I think that the constancy of the
speed of light is the constancy of it
well yes yes the the fact that it's the
same in every reference frame and the
fact that it's the same for all
particles now when I say it's the same
for all particles you say wait a minute
wait a minute protons don't move with a
speed of light the limiting veloc vity
for a proton is the speed of light so in
that sense it's very Universal so that's
the first thing we want to set c equal
to
one sounds like a good thing to do and
we do that all the time of course the
next thing which is very Universal is
Plank's constant let me give you an
example Plank's constant is not just
some any old constant like the radius of
a of a proton but it's connected with
the uncertainty principle for every
object in nature the uncertainty
principle between the momentum and its
position is greater than or equal to Har
bar there's maybe some four or some two
in there I don't remember but uh but it
doesn't matter what object you're
talking about you could be talking about
an electron you could be talking about a
proton you could be talking about a
bowling ball they are all constrained by
the same uncertainty principle and so in
that sense H bar and it doesn't much
matter whether you use H bar or the or H
you know the one without the 2 pi in it
that's not the point here the point is
that plunk constant applies to
everything in the world it's Universal
so the next thing you might want to use
not might but we will is to set H bar
equal to one so what's the last really
Universal is there another truly un ival
constant the gravitational constant
remember according to Newton every
object in the universe no matter what
it's made out of no matter what it is um
composed of every object in the
universe has a gravitational force which
is the product of the masses divided by
the distance squared times the universal
constant
G so
again something which applies to
everything are there units are there
units in
which c h bar and G are equal to one now
that's the same as asking the question
can you combine c h and g into a into a
combination that has units of mass can
you combine them into a combination that
has un units of length and you can you
combine them into a combination that has
units of time and the answer is yes uh
let's uh let's see let's do length we
want to do
length tell you what even better let's
do length
squared let's see if we can find a
combination of GH bar and C which has
units of length squared okay so here's
what we do just some simple dimensional
analysis everybody here knows how to do
dimensional
analysis okay we'll do some simple
dimensional analysis we want to find a
combination G to some power let's call
it P H bar to some other power
q and C to some other power
pqr which has
units of length I'm going to choose
length squared
let's say has units of length
squared now this doesn't mean it's equal
to length squared it means it has the
same
units sometimes people uh sometimes
people put a bracket around a thing like
that to indicate its units the units of
G to the p h to the Q C to the r should
be length squared I'm choosing length
squared to avoid a square root in the
final formula that's all all right
there's there here's another reason it
is widely believed that the fundamental
unit is a unit of area not a unit of
length but we'll come to that uh some
other time um but let's see if we can
let's see if we can find PQ and
R okay first question is what now we
have to figure out what the units the
conventional units of g h bar and CR are
the units of C that's easy what's the
units of
C
that's length over time
right what about the units of plunk
constant momentum
distance again l m t
yeah Mass momentum time momentum
momentum times distance right Delta X
Delta P Delta X Delta P so that a
length and then a momentum is a
mass times a velocity and a velocity is
a length over time so that's length
squared over
time length squared Mass over time
that's Plank's constant and the last one
the one that I can never really remember
these two I remember the one I can never
remember is
G but how do we figure out what the
units of G R acceleration equals mass G
* yeah we use we use one of the
equations that g appears in all right so
the four so here's an equation that uh
let's
see which was your
equation all right
acceleration
equals yeah we'll get that in a minute
but it's equal to mass g r Mass G over R
2 so that's length
squared acceleration is
what length per time
squared and again equal means uh uh
doesn't mean
equal so it's l Cub over
t^2 divided by m it looks like
huh
right okay let's now go through the
exercise can I say something by the way
that's like law where the mount the
Mount of you're right you're right
you're right it is like keer law okay so
now we have on the left side length
squared now let's go g to the power P
what's G
again all right so it's l
cubed over
t^2 times m in the denominator all right
so it's l to the 3 p t to the 2 p m to
the P right did I get that
right that's G to the P now what about H
bar to the Q H to the Q is length
squared length to the 2
q m to the 2
q no m to the
Q
and
then
t to the
Q did I get that
right okay and then the last one is
speed of light to the AR Power which is
length to the
r over time to the
r now all we have to
do is find three constants so that
everything on the right hand side
cancels out except two powers of
length Okay so the first thing you can
see is mass only appears in two places
Mass to the Q and Mass to the P so what
does that
say it says P better be equal to Q okay
so let's just set P equal to Q we now
know
that and we can cancel out the masses
that's done
now what else do we have we have to get
rid of all the times it looks like
huh all right so how many times do we
have we
have 2
p 2 p
plus Q is the same as P so that's
3p +
r equal Z
3 p + r is equal to
Z so that tells us that
R is equal to
minus 3
p did I do that right let's just
check we have 2 p 3 p + r = 0 r = - 3
p okay I hope I'm doing this right minus
p
did I make a mistake yeah yeah yeah but
Q is
p we've already figured out the Q is
p so if I'm not mistaken I think we can
get rid of all the
t's p is equal to
Q so let's see what we have we have p is
equal to q that looks like 5 p
boy do I not recognize
that 5
p l to 2 Q that's taken care of and now
R is what R is equal to minus 3 p yeah
and you're
done yeah 3 pus 5
P 5 P minus 3 p and you're done 2 p r we
get 2 p right we get 2 p all together 2
p 2 p and that now tells us what p is p
is equal to
1 okay so let's see what we have now p
is equal to 1 it tells us that the plunk
area this is the plunk area the plunk
area L squared is
g
h looks like over C cubed right uh C
cubed C
cubed
this is usually expressed by saying the
plunk length is the square of
this
okay the square root of it thank
you uh let's uh should we put in some
numbers my problem is I can never
remember what plunk constant
is anybody know pl's constant 10 to
the good 10 -
okay yeah g is 6 * 10- 11 which which is
about 10us
10 order of magnitude 10us 10 what is h
bar 10-
34 10 Theus
34 in in usual uh MKS units 10 Theus
34 and what is C
cubed uh C is uh 10 3 * 10 8 3 * 3 10 17
oh my God how
many time 10 the minus how big is uh 24
10-
24 I think it's more like 10us 25 huh or
10us
25 so how many square meters is
this uh pretty
small pretty small yeah some some some
tiny tiny number okay um the plunk
length is very small if if we had done
it right we would have gotten 10 the -
35 M so 10 the should be 10 Theus 70th
Square cmers I'm not sure I got
everything
right
H yes about 70 all right so that's small
that's smaller than
anything what's
that good okay now the plunk time that's
uh the plunk length is the square root
of
this what about the plunk time think of
the plunk length as being the size of a
little thingy right there's a thing the
size of the plunk Lane what do you think
the plunk time
is it's the time for a light rate to
cross that thing right what else could
it be right so it's the time for a light
rate to cross that little distance so
does that mean that means we have to uh
divide it by the speed of light
yeah we have to divide it by the speed
of light so the plunk length L plun is
10 to Theus 35
M the um plunk time is 10 to the
minus 43 or 42 something like that 42
seconds 10- 44 43 seconds something like
that now what about the plunk Mass
we haven't figured out what the plunk
mass is but we could do exactly the same
calculation work out what the plunk mass
is
um H from H from har bar from H bar and
the plunk
Mass would be about 10 to the minus
um 8
kilog so this one's big that's a big
Mass
10us 8 kilg is a observable thing a
little it's a little dust
grain it's a little dust
grain these are impossibly small small
times and small
distances okay this is the uh plunk
units things measured in these plunk
units are measured in some very very
fundamental uh units okay I'll tell you
some things the universe as a radius the
uh the known observable universe The
Horizon size is about 10 to the 60th
plunk lengths 10 to the 60th plunk
lengths the age of the universe is also
about 10 to the 60th plunk
times
uh
and good that's
uh and a gallon of uh sorry a tank of
gas
gasoline is about the an energy content
a tank of
gasoline is about the plunk
Mass okay so that means you could drive
across the country with 10 plunk masses
of energy okay right that's what it
means these are the units that string
theory is in
there the size of a vibrating string the
fluctuations in it due to Quantum
uncertainty order of magnitude the plunk
length the frequencies of oscillation or
the time not the frequency but the
period of oscillation of order 10 Theus
cm sorry sorry 10us 43 seconds right and
the amount of
mass
that would be involved in exciting a
fundamental particle such as a graviton
or an electron let's take the electron
if the electron is a string you could
ask how much energy does it take to
excite it the units are expected to be
somewhere in this range 10 Theus 8 uh
kilog now that's a huge number how many
uh how many gevs gig electron volts is
at
one other useful number to meor to
remember is that one plun mass is about
10 to the
19th gevs which means 10 to the 19th
proton
masses one plank mass is about 10 to the
19th proton
masses 10 to the 23rd proton masses is
you know a little gram of water or
something 10 the 19th which is four ERS
of magnitude smaller is a tiny tiny
little droplet but visible quite visible
well if you have good eyes so um so
exciting an
electron by a particle physics Collision
you say well we don't need to do a
particle physics Collision we'll just
explode a tank of gazoline in the
vicinity of an electron and it will
start the electron vibrating yeah it's
just a rather hard to get the energy to
be concent ated in such a small uh such
a small
distance
so it um these are the reasons that
uh
that yeah above its ground state ground
state no
well remember it's Mass squares which
come in integer
multiples all right so it's Mass squares
which come in integer multiples so if
you want to know what the unit is square
the plunk mass and that's the amount
that it takes to bump you up but to go
but to go from the ground state if the
ground state is almost
massless then it's about one plunk unit
of energy that's why you
can't right right right it's just much
too much energy to pump into such a
small
volume and um you know it's it's for
this reason that
[Music]
uh that string theory is way way be
direct direct um
detection how would you detect that a
thing is a string the same way you
detect that a proton is a string you hit
it you set it into vibration and you
discover that there's a bunch of excited
states where the mass squared is
proportional to the angular
momentum that's the kind of thing you'd
like to do with an electron that's the
kind of thing that you'd like to do I'll
be right with you Michael uh that's the
kind of thing You' like to do with a
photon but the increase in Mass here is
just Way Beyond what can be done yeah in
order to have the structure of the
string that we've been describing yeah
wouldn't the the string as a whole have
to be somewhat bigger than this
right mhm
Yeah
question question this is just a bunch
of arithmetic over here
what makes us think that when we get a
number out 10us 35th that it has
anything to do with the length of a
string it's a
guess it's a
guess it's a guess um based on a number
of
things no no it's not just no
no no it's not just
numerology
um
it could be
wrong it could be a thousand times less
nobody thinks that the string length
scale could be smaller than the plunk
length that that looks quite impossible
but that the string length scale could
be larger and the energy scale lower
that is possible how much lower well I
think from the things that we know about
particle
physics we can't say with any Precision
at the current time really at all but
um from the Precision with which
uh particle
physics standard model and so forth seem
to
work I think there's plenty of evidence
that the energy scale is very very high
whether it's plank scale or a 100th of
the plank scale or a thousandth of the
plunk scale we don't know uh there is
another scale in physics there is
another scale in physics which keeps
coming up over and over again we've
talked about it it's the unification
scale if you remember at all from last
quarter we talked about the scale at
which the various coupling constants
seem to come
together the scale at which the electro
weak forces and the qcd forces seem to
merge into a common structure
experimentally and there there there are
experiments
not experiments to get to that energy
but experiments to extrapolate the
extrapolation of what we know about
physics seems to say that ordinary
Quantum field Theory probably holds to
something like a distant scale
no of roughly a thousand times uh larger
than the plunk
scale so we do have evidence that uh
that ordinary Quantum field Theory
without any stringy structures and so
forth or equivalently that the electron
is fundamental to scales um perhaps a
thousand times uh smaller sorry a
thousand times larger than the plunk
scale but that's that's still pretty
small then you wouldn't be able to
suspend the Galaxy maybe you could only
take suspend
um oh I don't know some globular cluster
somewhere but
yeah um it it seems that a a plank left
can be thought of as the fundamental
unit of small as un of L in the plank
time smallest unit of
time clearly a plank mass is not
fundamental unit of mass
no
no plun mass is believed to be the mass
of the lightest possible black
hole area one plunk area one unit of
entropy and how long would it take to
evaporate one plunk
time here today
gone today
today you show the coupling coefficient
unifying I you showed the coupling
coefficients unifying I believe one time
we put down a fourth one for Gravity so
that comes down M that's that's a
connection what's the C that's that's
okay I'll tell you what the various
pieces of evidence are I'm not going to
explain them in detail I just this is
just to remind you if you
plot the coupling
constants of which coupling constants
the ones that we measure in the
laboratory the um uh the electric let's
just call it the elect electric coupling
constant uh
e e^ s really the weak intera uh sorry
Electro Electro
week I'm getting there are three of
them there U1 su2 and su3 there are
three of them this is energy this way
and energy is the same as inverse
length inverse length so as energy gets
large wavelengths get short energy high
energy means small distance okay we
measure these coupling constants at some
energy scales remember coupling
constants are things which change with
energy or change with distance scale we
measure them somewhere where in
Laboratories which
means 50 gev 100 gev at most we measure
them here we get three
numbers we
also measure
slightly
indirectly the derivatives of these
things in fact we can compute the
derivatives of them we can compute the
derivatives of them purely theoretically
but with good confidence because we know
the theory here very
well what we find is that if you
extrapolated these they would all cross
at about a common
point
that point and that point is way way out
here and an energy which is not the
plunk scale but it's about a 100 or
maybe a thousand times somewhere between
100 and a th000 times smaller than the
plunk scale I think maybe more like a
100 so this could be M
plun roughly divided by 100 somewhere in
between and the plank scale would be
over here or this is a logarithmic scale
and a logarithmic scale it looks like
this so on a logarithmic scale a given
Gap can mean a very very big change in
energy and it looks like
this now of course we don't know with
certainty that there's not all kinds of
things going on at higher energy here
which would muck this up badly we don't
but what we do know is that is that if
there is nothing in here to muck things
up badly and there's some reason to
believe that that these coupling
constants would just come together at
the scale the meaning of that is that
Quantum field Theory conventional
Quantum field Theory seems to be working
to about here there's other evidence for
this scale coming from nutrino masses
and a few other
places uh but it's far from tight it
will become much tighter if LHC is lucky
and makes the right discoveries it will
become much tighter and uh we'll have a
much better knowledge about this
extrapolation so this is one of the
things we're going to learn from LHC is
how reliable this extrapolation
is plunk Mass being out
here and this in itself doesn't tell us
where the string length scale is what it
tells us is that the stringy character
of particles does not become important
until energy is above this so somewhere
between here and here if string theory
is all right somewhere in here scale
Str remind me again what the three
coupling constants are there's what is
it QED Q QC and gravity no QED qcd and
the weak interactions oh weak yeah at
one point you did put down I think you
put down something for Gravity put down
yeah yeah if you were to plot the the
gravitational coupling constant behaves
differently has a different character
but let's see um it starts very very
small and it goes up something like this
and it would
cross it doesn't cross at the same point
it crosses somewhere
nearby but basically the place where
this one gets to be about order one
that's the plunk scale so it really it's
really exactly the same statement to say
that the gravitational constant the
running coupling constant crosses at
roughly the same place as to say this
unification scale is not too far from
the pl does that con depend upon capital
G yes so does capital G change as you uh
as you start to measure higher and
higher energy okay I'll uh no capital G
does not change but capital G is not
exactly the right measure of things it's
capital
G all right let's let's do I'll answer
your question let's look at the force
law between two objects in
electromagnetism it's
e^2 / R
2 and that's the
force and that's the electromagnetic
coupling constant here in
gravitation it's G m^2 over R
2 so the thing which is analogous to e^2
is G * m^2 but what M should you use
there well the M that you use
there is associated with the particular
scale of physics that you're
studying all right so you can see then
in that sense this quantity here
increases like M
squ yeah so this is the this is the
relevant thing here it's the
dimensionless
thing
okay um that's
units U where on that scale uh if you
could build accelerators big enough is
it that you start producing nothing but
little black holes real black holes yeah
the small ones you know if you build
galaxies oh it's all the way out there
qu MK
yeah there's two ways to produce black
holes one way or another you've got to
have a lot of pressure to squeeze things
into a small volume one way is kinetic
energy small objects with lots of
kinetic energy blast them together and
you have a chance of making a black hole
the other way is not kinetic energy but
gravitation gravitational potential
energy pulling things together that
takes a
star so to make a black hole using
gravity you need something as heavy as a
star to make a black hole by the
Collision of particles you need energies
um of order the plunk energy now if you
think about that for a minute imagine an
accelerator
uh I don't know is it fun to let's let's
explore the following question how big
what kind of accelerator would it take
to uh to do experiments at the plunk
energy to do interesting experiments of
the plunk energy well basically the
energy of an acceler Ator of a linear
accelerator scales linearly with the uh
with the size of the accelerator you get
a certain number of gev per unit length
slack is a good example it takes
approximately 2 miles to accelerate a
thing to uh uh to 100 gev so 2 miles for
gev 2 miles 100 gev
all right the plunk energy is about 10
to the 17th times
bigger than this it's 10 to the 19th gev
so it's 10 to the 17th times larger so
with just the just the the parameters of
the slack accelerator you can multiply
this by roughly 10 to the 17th so it
would take 10 to the 17th miles how big
is 10 to the 17th miles
oh man um 10 to the 7 uh 10 to the I
think 10 to the 13th miles is about a
lightyear 10 to 13 kilometers or
something like that if I remember 10 to
13 kilm 10 to 17 10 to the 4 light
years Galaxy size Galaxy size to uh to
accelerate something up the plunk Mass
we're not going to do it at least at
least not tomorrow okay but suppose you
could build such an
accelerator next question what kind of
Lumin Luminosity do you have to have an
accelerator has to have a
Luminosity um the chances of what we
want to do now is we want to collide
particles headon to make a black hole
but remember the radius of that black
hole that we want to make is itself the
plunk Mass the plunk radius so that
means we've got to aim these particles
to collide within a plunk distance well
no accelerators don't do that that's not
the way accelerators work the way
accelerators work is you just get a lot
of particles going to the left a lot of
particles going to the right and you get
enough of them so that some will collide
at the distant scales that you're
interested in in other words you need
big
Luminosity what kind of Luminosity would
you need oh I don't know let's
say what a slack Luminosity 10 to the
13th particles per a second or something
anybody
know I don't know well 10 to the 13th
particles but that's just but you know
the distance scales there are pretty big
how much better are you going to have to
do I don't know let's say 10 to the 20th
particles 10 to the 20th particles
colliding each with the plunk energy
that's 10 to the 20th tanks of gasoline
per
second 10 not yeah 10 to the 17th
barrels of gas per second to fuel it as
big as the Galaxy we ain't going to do
it that's what we would need to
explore small black holes and something
pretty close to it to explore String
Theory directly a really direct
test the question is are there indirect
tests all right I think this the
indirect tests will pretty much be very
theoretical and unless somebody
constructs a very very convincing string
theory that gives rise to the standard
model exactly in some very comput
mutable way the
uh the hope of direct tests I think is
very
remote
uh so that's that's that's what we're
facing that's what we're up
against okay um
we didn't get where I really had
intended to go in fact we didn't even
touch on what I intended to uh touch
on extra Dimensions that you had talked
about are they in the range of the
planks in this thirus 35 oh which
Dimensions the extra dimensions of yes
yes it is believed again without really
terrific evidence but again it's the
same kind of evidence it's the same
where is it where is our plot of
coupling
constants if there were extra dimensions
and the extra Dimensions had any sizable
distance if they were at all
sizable then ordinary Quantum field
Theory would break
down when particles begin exploring the
extra Dimensions the conventional use of
quantum field Theory as we use it would
break
down at points where the energy became
large enough to explore these extra tiny
Dimensions if it's true and if we
continue to get evidence that Quant
field Theory makes sense as it is out to
these distances here then we'll know
that the extra
Dimensions must
lie somewhere as between the plunk
length and maybe a thousand times bigger
than the plunk length so exploring extra
Dimensions will also be something that
is extremely indirect and extremely hard
why couldn't it be significantly or is a
b to less than the thought is that
what's the argument if if it orders of
magnitude a that's another question
that's another question there the theory
really doesn't uh work at all under
those
circumstances
um let's put it this way if you try to
make them
smaller than the plunk length you would
wind up making their Mass larger than
the plunk
Mass making a small
thing with big Mass means you make
a
black hole black hole so if you're
trying to think of strings which were
much smaller than the plunk
distance and their Mass would
accordingly be larger than the plunk
Mass you would be talking about black
holes you wouldn't be talking about
strings that's the problem they would
collapse the gravit the gravit their
mass and their small distance would
cause gravitation basically to turn them
into black holes so that's the reason
that the string theorists do not ever
consider the possibility that the string
scale is smaller than the plunk mass and
I think it's a very good
reason did you say that the mass here is
derived from the choice for L from the
what uh well you gave us why we have a l
why we have a t yeah yeah but you you do
exactly the same thing you say let's
make a mass squared out of these
parameters here and I forget exactly
what it is we could figure it out but
there's but the others were a physical
Choice sorry the other length of time
were a physical Choice what do you mean
they're physical they're all physical
well yeah but I
mean uh the time for example is the time
to cross yeah a length yeah and what is
that's a physical quantity well H part
is physical
too and what did you say about Mass you
just put it down well you does it follow
from our choices from
LT yes it does um well no it doesn't
follow by itself from Lent
P but if you
asked um ah good let's see once you have
L&T you can get Mass from either H bar
or
G yeah you could ask here's the way to
think about it take two
particles whose distance
apart is the plunk length now because
their distan is so small
the uncertainty principle says that they
have a lot of
energy okay right the uncertainty
principle says if things are very well
localized then they have very large
momentum the fluctuations in the
momentum are very large so take two
particles whose distance is known to be
within the plunk
distance and that says something about
their momentum their average momentum is
extremely large and from that you can
compute what their average kinetic
energy of these two particles
are that kinetic energy will be the
plunk Mass so two particles if you try
to take two particles and localize them
to a distance comparable to the plunk
distance the answer will be that the
uh that the energy that you have to put
in to do that will be the plunk Mass so
it's just uncertainty principle we could
work it out but uh
yeah right
okay let's take a
rest I'm going to tell you next
about some mathematics I'm going to tell
you about the mathematics of conformal
Transformations why because that's the
basic mathematical tool of string
theory well we have our choice I can
either tell you why there are 24 or 26
dimensions in string theory or I can
start to tell you about conformal
Transformations we'll get to both of
them at some point but uh we CL
Thanksgiving yeah uh as long as it's not
on Thanksgiving Thanksgiving is always
Thursday so I think the answer is
yes okay we have 45
minutes and I will try and 45
minutes to give
you the easy version of why there have
to be 26 dimensions in bosonic string
theory the easy version is not
easy
and it
uh doesn't really get to the root of
it the hard version is is very
hard but that doesn't mean that we can't
exp we can't talk about it qualitatively
but I thought I would do the what I call
the easy version which is not easy and
not satisfying but nevertheless is
correct Let's
uh and you know when people see this
they walk away and uh say uh um gee
that's a that's sort of magic but in the
bad
sense but it is correct and it is sort
of the
way that the uh that the need for extra
Dimensions was
discovered it has to do if you
remember in order to get the photon to
come out
right we had to do something odd we had
to take the mass
squared of the ground state of the
oscillating
string you remember let's take the open
string Tak in the case of the open
string the mass squared had to be um
minus one
unit that was so that when we applied a
creation operator to create the photon
polarization it came out
massless minus one one unit on top of
that gives us something massless we
haven't talked yet about how we get rid
of this particle of negative Mass
squared I assure you that can be gotten
rid of but um let's uh let's not worry
about it let's agree the mass squared of
the ground state is
minus1 why is it minus1 how do we how do
we get minus one well harmonic
oscillators have Zero Point
Energy so the ground state energy of
this vibration in string should be
nothing but the sum total of all of the
Zer Point energies of the vibrating
string zero point energies are all
positive and in fact they depend on the
frequency anybody remember what the Zero
Point Energy of a harmonic oscillator
is a half har Omega let's forget H bar
set it equal to one 12 Omega and do you
remember the frequenc of the N harmonic
oscillator it was just
n in each one each one of the
oscillating modes of the
string there's the string each one of
the oscillating
modes the nth oscillating mode has
frequency n so the ground state energy
of the nth oscillator is just n/ two in
some units is is n
/2 now this doesn't sound good we have a
lot of
oscillators one for each
integer we have to add up all that
energy it's not quite easy to imagine
how we can add all this up and get minus
one right so so there's something
strange going on okay and there
is but actually we don't have to get
minus1 we have to get to something a
little bit different let's go back to
the energy of a very very fast moving
system the energy of a very very fast
moving system has first of all it has
the overall momentum moving down the
z-axis it has the overall moment
momentum and then on top of the overall
and that's a conserved quantity and we
really don't care about it very much
since it never changes during the
processes that take place in particle
physics and
then for a particle which is not moving
for whose Center of mass is not moving
um in the plane what's the what's the
rest of it you
remember the mass
squared divided I think by twice the
momentum
and that's why we began to identify the
energy non-relativistic energy with m s
rather than
M this was the
energy and to make precise this idea
of very rapid systems which become
non-relativistic you have to let P
become extremely large basically you
have to take the limit of an infinitely
large
momentum in the limit of infinitely
momentum uh this is the form that the
energy takes you say well wait I don't
take the form of infinitely large energy
this thing just goes to zero but what
you really do is you take e minus P you
subtract the momentum from the energy
that's all right this is a perfectly
conserved quantity never changes if it
never changes you don't care very much
about it and then multiply the whole
thing by let's say 2 p and that gives
you
M2 this 2 p here the reason you multiply
by 2 p is that's got to do with time
dilation the faster a thing moves down
the z-axis the slower its internal
motions go the slower the internal
motions that means the smaller the
internal energies for example if you
have an
atom what's the ionization energy of a
hydrogen atom
13.5 electron volts or something okay
now you take that atom and you speed it
up and you send it down in other words
the energy difference between the ground
state of the atom let's not take the uh
the ionization energy the energy
difference between the ground state of a
hydrogen atom and the first excited
state is
what I know 3 four volts something like
that three or four three or four
electron volts now what happens as you
boost the
atom what happens to the overall energy
of it it increases of course right
that's this but what happens to the
energy difference between the um between
the first excited state and or between
the ground state and the second and the
first excited state does it get bigger
or smaller smaller and it gets smaller
with this one over P here and in fact
the energy of that atom or the
differences of energy between the atoms
are proportional to the square of the
mass of the
atom / 2p so that's what this formula is
well we don't want to we don't care
about this piece that just has to do
with its overall motion down the z-axis
just subtract it off it doesn't have to
do with the internal
motions and then the p and the
denominator here that's just associated
with the slowing down of the internal
motions so let's just multiply through
by it and this is the way we really
think of energy this quantity is the
energy and it's proportional to the mass
squared okay the point is now that the
actual
energy of the ground state has an
infinite piece a piece
or let's put this piece back let's put
let's not subtract this let's add this
back on this side plus what is it + p ^
2 + 2 p ^
2 uh let me just get this right P * e
let's take P * e is m^2 + 2
p^2 okay notice that first of all
there's the interesting thing which is
the mass squared which we're interested
in but there's also this infinite piece
here this infinite
piece so it's not really quite true that
the that the energy has to add up to
minus1 it would be okay if it added up
to something like minus1 plus an
infinite constant that was similar to p^
squ so I'm going to show you how that
works I'm going show you how that works
how you can add
up 1 + 2+ 3+ 4 plus 5 this is all the
internal energy and get something which
looks
like a
constant namely minus one which is what
we want to get plus an infinite piece
that can be absorbed into something
that's already there this is a trick of
physics that takes place all the time
you it's it happens all the time in all
kinds of context where you get some
infinite answer and you don't know what
to do with the infinite answer but you
realize that there was that the thing
which is becoming in infinite already
has a constant piece in it that you just
add the extra Infinity to the constant
piece an example is the energy of vacuum
the energy of uh just the mass of a a
mass of a particle there are self
energies all sorts of things like that
where you can hide infinite constants
into things which are already there I'm
not saying this is a satisfactory State
of Affairs it's just something that we
do all the time the energy in this
room it has zero point oscillations from
all of the photons and everything else
not from the photons that are here but
from the uh oscillations of the
electromagnetic field how big are those
oscillations the energy infinite what do
we do with it we just subtract it off by
saying we could add a constant to the
energy of the room and it wouldn't make
any difference so just get rid of it the
same thing here we're going to get
constant piece which is just infinite
but constant as as long as it's constant
it never affects anything plus a term
which looks like
this with a uh with an additional Mass
squared um let me show you the
mathematics and we can then discuss
another time the physics the mathematics
is tricky but uh but
easy the mathematics is just a question
of adding up 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4 it's
just a sum here okay 1 + 2 + 3 + 4 where
there's an overall factor of a half
outside that comes from the half from
the half H bar Omega but the basic
calculation is to add up all of the
integers it's obviously infinite okay
but let's see if we can extract out of
that infinite piece an
infinity plus something finite this is
always the way Quantum field Theory and
uh and uh Rel relativistic quantum
mechanics
works okay so 1 plus 2 plus 3 + 4 this
is not something we're going to easily
add up is it so let's do something to it
and then take a limit let's take the
let's do something to it so that it
makes sense and then take a limit let's
multiply each one of
these but let's let's introduce a small
constant
Epsilon e to the minus Epsilon is a
number less than one
but when Epsilon is very very
small this number is close to one right
okay let's add to it+
2 eus 2
Epsilon this is just a trick for making
the sum converge each term in it we're
going to put in something which gets
smaller and smaller but when Epsilon
goes to
zero it'll just give us back the
original sum soep is going to go to zero
in fact you know what well yeah all
right let's leave it this way 1 + 2
Epsilon what's the next one 3 e to-3
Epsilon + 4 e-4
Epsilon but now if
Epsilon is not
zero then the sequence of terms eus
Epsilon eus 2 Epsilon eus 3 Epsilon do
get smaller and smaller now if Epsilon
is small it takes a long long time for
them to
shrink so if we were just to plot the e
to the minus Epsilon e to Theus 2
Epsilon be a very as a function of the
integers it would fall very slowly if
Epsilon is a small
number right but
eventually the e to the minus n Epsilon
will win and it will be make each term
successively smaller and smaller and
you'll be able to add them up right so
what you do is you add these up and then
after adding them up you let Epsilon go
to zero right it's a mathematical trick
so let's see what uh let's see what we
get it takes a bunch of steps and I'll
show you but the steps are uh the steps
are
Elementary okay
um
this can be written as the sum from n =
1 to
Infinity of n e to Theus n
Epsilon e to theus1 Epsilon * 1 eus 2
Epsilon * 2 and so forth and so on right
that the that's the
sum now the trick is to get rid of this
n first trick is to get rid of this n
and the way to get rid of this n
is just to diff is to take the sum
without the n in it and differentiate
with respect to Epsilon what happens if
we differentiate with respect to
Epsilon what does the derivative with
respect to Epsilon
give it brings down minus n all right so
this is equal to
minus so no we want to we really want to
put minus here this is equal to the
original sum we were interested in NE
eus n
Epsilon okay that's the first
step next step is to
observe that we can add the series up
this whole series is a geometric series
it starts out let's just see what it is
it has an e to the minus Epsilon plus an
e to Theus 2
Epsilon plus an e to Theus 3
Epsilon
which also can be written in another
form it's e to the minus Epsilon times
1 + eus Epsilon plus eus 2 Epsilon and
so
forth I pulled out a factor of e to the
minus Epsilon do you know what this
is exactly this is a geometric series
one
plus a number plus the square of the
number plus the cube of the
number and so we can add all of this
up and what do we get we get e to Theus
Epsilon divided by 1 minus E to the
minus
Epsilon okay
that's that's the thing that we want to
differentiate with respect to
Epsilon that's this put a minus sign in
front of
it okay this is this is
something uh you can do it home for
homework but I'm going to show you
roughly what
happens oh but in the end we're
interested in small Epsilon we're
interested in small Epsilon so
um let's
uh let's see what do we want to do with
that yeah know
let's expand it for small Epsilon let's
first expand it for small Epsilon and
then do the operation and they'll
Epsilon go to zero we're interested in
small Epsilon so what is e to the minus
Epsilon when expanded in terms of
Epsilon 1 - Epsilon plus Epsilon 2 / 2
dot dot dot we're only going to need
things to power Epsilon squar we won't
need things beyond that
and of course there are more but we
won't need
them now what about the
denominator what's in the
denominator we have one
minus okay so let's write out e to the
minus
Epsilon
1 I think it's plus Epsilon minus
SAR what let's go to the next one I
think we're going to need the next one
as you'll see uh ex Epsilon s over two
right what's the next
one let me just check the sign 1 - 1
plus Epsilon - Epsilon 2 over 2 and the
next
one plus Epsilon
cubed over what over Epsilon
cubed over 6 right
now we have
trouble the trouble is the ones
cancel the
denominator is proportional to Epsilon
let's factor out one power of
Epsilon Let's see we want to take the
derivative this is this is the object
whose derivative we want to
take let's factor out a factor of
Epsilon in the denominator since
everything in the denominator has
Epsilon let's Factor it out 1 over
Epsilon and then this becomes
1 - Epsilon plus Epsilon 2 did everybody
follow
that okay plus higher terms but as I
said the higher terms are going to
disappear when we uh when we go to uh
small Epsilon they won't be
important did I loose lose a minus sign
I
was
well I thought I got it
right all right let's should we do it
over
one
minus put in Brackets
one -
Epsilon plus Epsilon 2 / 2 - Epsilon
cubed / 6 all right everybody happy with
that now the ones are going to
cancel
and the minus times the minus will make
plus minus
plus I have no idea if that's what I had
written down before or
not then we pull out a factor of
Epsilon and that turns this into 1 -
Epsilon / 2 plus Epsilon 2ar /
all right now the trick is we're
expanding everything in powers of
Epsilon but here we have a thing in the
denominator I don't want this in the
denominator I want in the numerator so
how do you deal with a thing in the
denominator like
this you use the formula that
1 minus a small number let's just call
it s is equal to 1 + S + s²
plus s
[Music]
cubed and so
forth here's your
s oh did I did I leave out something no
I think I got it right
did did I I think I did everything right
I think I did everything right so what
we do is we take what's in the
denominator here and we expand it to get
all the Epsilon dependents in the
numerator let's see what we get I think
we're going to get 1 plus epon / 2 -
Epsilon 2 /
6 but then there's a term coming from
squaring the small quantity here if I
keep things to order Epsilon squar all
I'm going to get is let's see I think
plus Epsilon 2ar over 4 I
think but you can expand it out yourself
um something like this
plus higher order in
epsilon no I think it was Epsilon
squared
mhm it was just Epsilon squar it's not
Epsilon
cubed now the thing which was Epsilon
cubed in the denominator here became
Epsilon squar when I pulled out the
Epsilon here and I was purposefully
keeping everything to pow's order
Epsilon squar I know that the next order
is not
important okay so let's see if we can
combine this together I think the
chances that I'll get this right are
negligible but uh all right so we get
minus d by D
Epsilon 1/
Epsilon uh times okay 1 * 1 let's put in
everything that you get from one 1 plus
Epsilon over 2
minus Epsilon 2 over 6 oh uh can we
combine these two
together what's Epsilon 2 4 - Epsilon 2
6 Epsilon 2
right okay how did you do that so fast
who did
it
you
what took me about 30 minutes to get
that Epsilon squ over
okay you
know I know I know how to do
it one plus Epsilon minus EP uh sorry 1
plus Epsilon s over 12 right
that's this times this this and this
then we get minus
Epsilon minus
Epsilon * 1 and
then uh - Epsilon 2 /
2 but then from here we get something of
order Epsilon cubed and I'm not
interested in keeping anything of order
Epsilon cubed that's too high in order I
don't care about it
we'll see why in a moment and then we
have plus Epsilon ^ 2 /
2 and nothing past that because the next
one would
be Epsilon 4th I think this is
everything to order Epsilon
squared should it be
plus
no
I think it should be plus right yeah
right looks right 1 * Epsilon 2
12 okay now Epsilon over 2 - Epsilon
that's minus Epsilon over two we get rid
of
this and these two
cancel so there's our formula right
there as you'll see anything of higher
order is not going to be interesting to
us
okay look at let's f f f first focus on
the one that's easiest the easiest term
is this Epsilon over two it gets
multiplied by 1 over Epsilon that means
it's just 1/2 and what happens when you
differentiate 1/2 with respect to
Epsilon is zero so this is we don't have
to write it it's not it's not
there okay now we have a term which is
one/ Epsilon that's bad news this is
this is uh something infinite at Epsilon
equals 0 and remember we're going to go
to Epsilon equals
0 all right what's what's the derivative
of 1/
Epsilon minus 1 over Epsilon SAR right -
1 Epsilon
2ar
oh and there's another minus sign here
so that's plus 1/ Epsilon squar I
think
yes and
then 1 / Epsilon time
Epsilon the ep one of the epsilons
cancel and then you differentiate with
respect to Epsilon what do you
get -
112th
this is a famous
formula which is usually stated half
jokingly that 1 + 2 + 3+ 4+ 5 is equal
to minus a 12th they tend to forget
about this term over
here okay and the reason is that this
term combines
well this term is an infinite
constant
which really does doesn't
uh I would have to convince you that
where it of what happens to it it gets
absorbed into the P squar the P squar
term in the energy the infinite term in
the energy and a careful anal really
careful analysis of
it um allows you to absorb this into
something into into an additive constant
in the energy that doesn't do anything
anything for the moment you'll have to
accept that uh the real answer the
really right answer the really right
answer is that in good string theories
properly defined string theories this
isn't there
altogether but I'm not going to tell you
why now I'm not going to tell you why
now I'm just going to tell you this
infinite
constant is not
important
you know the famous story of dra and poy
that uh that dur calculated the vacuum
energy and found out that it was
infinite and they said uh well since
it's infinite I don't care about it
we'll throw it away and probably turned
around to him and said just because it's
infinite doesn't mean it's
zero
right right well in this particular case
the rack wins the rack wins but this is
something we will have to come back to
and explain why this one over Epsilon
squared remember Epsilon is going to go
to zero this is going to be an infinite
constant and in this particular case the
infinite constant really is not
important and I'm not going to pursue it
right now I'm going to tell you the
answer is minus a
12th okay minus a 12th now this is not
yet a particularly good
answer this is not a particularly good
answer yet remember what we wanted to
get was Al together minus one we wanted
to get this
minus1 which when we excite it by one
unit of energy will give us the massless
particle okay in fact the minus of 12 is
not quite right and the reason is
because of this factor of a half from
the half H
Omega so it's actually one
24 1 over
24 that minus 1 over 24 is the energy of
the ground state including the zero
point oscillations but throwing away a
certain infinite term which we're going
to have to explain away
later
uh
but okay how do we get oh oh have I left
anything out
I left out one
thing remember for each mode there are
is not one oscillator but two
oscillators the A's and the B's remember
the A's and the B's the X oscillators
and the Y oscillators so actually it's
twice
this twice this one for the X
oscillators one for the Y oscillators
it's still not good it's only 2 over -4
we really want to get minus
one right how do you get minus one you
say there weren't two dimensions of
oscillation there were 2 24 of
them 24 directions of
oscillation plus the direction going
down the
z-axis plus time make
26 that's where the 26 is all right now
this is a crazy story at the time nobody
believed it
uh that this is a little bit too silly
to be true but in fact the mathematics
did fit together mathematics and this is
the simplest way this this which is
fairly complicated already is the
simplest way to see and it is
historically the way it came about that
uh that
requiring let's say there are D
dimensions of space perpendicular to the
direction of motion then requiring this
to come out to be minus one just just so
that when you excite it you can get the
photon that uh that was the original
argument about the
um uh about D having to be 24 or the
total SpaceTime Dimension having to be
26 now as I said there the arguments
this
was uh hardly a convincing argument at
the
time its virtue is that it's easy to
Pres
present relatively easy to
present what what is the history what
was the uh history of this introduction
Ian is that where how did this come
about yeah well I was just wondering
1990s or oh God no
1969 yeah
69 no no no this goes back to
19 yeah 1969 I would say maybe maybe
early 70 but I think it's still
69 yes well by this point people would
just exploring the mathematics of string
theory and they had
and
um well experimentally you had the reg
trajectories but at some point when the
mathematical structure was put in place
people began to explore it for its own
sake all right it was realized rather
quickly
that uh there was some kind of funny
thing going on that there was a spin one
particle one unit up one unit up from
but it didn't have all the states that
it needed it had two polarizations and
not three
polarizations and it was realized rather
quickly that this could only be the
photon or something like a
photon but that then left the
question what was this Zero Point Energy
that had to be minus one and it it was
realized fairly quickly that that
required 25 24 dimensions of
oscillation now as I said this was uh by
no means a convincing argument other
much much much more convincing arguments
came about but they were highly
mathematical really highly
mathematical and I I'll tell you about
them in words but not now we need one
more mathematical concept is there a
similar trick to get
eight get
eight yes yes there it's a similar trick
to get eight but uh before I tell you
that let me go back to the Clos
string remember the C string you had to
excite
twice you had to get spin two you had to
hit it with two
oscillators that meant that the ground
state had to have minus two units of
energy okay but now we have a problem D
over 24 if D is 24 is only minus one
what's the answer 4
48 why 48 get a minus two 11 12th right
get the minus two yeah yeah but where do
I know but you only have 24 directions
we can't change the number of directions
of space when you go from close from
closed
strings no no no the same Theory the
same theory has both closed and open
strings you you can't change that right
you can't do that no we'll agree the
theory has 24 Dimensions now what
happens to the Clos string circular par
circular par all right well something
like that remember you have twice as
many oscillators for the Clos strings
you got the ones that go around to the
left and you got the ones that go around
to the right everything gets doubled
once again you have not only an
oscillation for every direction of space
but you have one for right goinging
modes and one for left-going modes so in
fact it's true that you get twice as
many which means that the ground state
energy is minus 2 which is just exactly
the right thing so that two units of
oscillation will bring you up to
massless
again that began to smell
better it began to smell smell better
but still far from uh far from a
convincing
argument the real thing has to do with
something called conformal invariance so
we're going to take up con formal
invariance next time what conformal
invariance
means if you want to prepare yourself
learn a little bit about complex
function Theory very little not much
we're going to do a very little bit
learn what the Koshi reman equations are
if not I will explain
it
uh
and we will come to why
string
theory is the theory of Turkish
taffy you know what Turkish Taff you
pull it this way you pull it that way
you stretch it out that way you stick it
together and somehow it all stays
together
uh conformal
Transformations anyway I think we're
finished for tonight
we've Koshi reman
equations
couchy
couchy just learn a little bit about
them for more please visit us at
stanford.edu